Guide to the Samuel Flagg Bemis Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Samuel Flagg Bemis papers
1798-1969
MS 74
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
34.5
(68 boxes, 1 folio)
The papers consist of correspondence, lecture notes, research materials, manuscripts (both published and unpublished), a complete set of printed works, clippings, photographs and memorabilia. Correspondence, both professional and personal, make up the bulk of the papers.
Bemis, Samuel Flagg, 1891-1973
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Samuel F. Bemis, 1966-1973, and of Yale University History Department, 1969. Transfer from Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, 2008.
Biographical / Historical
Samuel Flagg Bemis taught history at Colorado College from 1917-1920, at Whitman College from 1920-1923, and at George Washington University from 1924-1934. He was director of the European mission of the Library of Congress from 1927-1929. Bemis was a professor of history at Yale University from 1935-1973. He was the author of numerous books and articles, and received the Pulitzer Prize in 1926 and 1950.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of correspondence, lecture notes, research materials, manuscripts (both published and unpublished), a complete set of printed works, clippings, photographs and memorabilia. Correspondence, both professional and personal, make up the bulk of the papers.
Arrangement
The papers are organized in two series: I General Correspondence, 1918-1969 and II. Organization and Project Files, 1918-1969.
Armed Forces; Latin America; Lecture notes; Photoprints; Historians; Bemis, Samuel Flagg, 1891-1973; Yale University -- Faculty; Yale University. Department of History
- General Correspondence, 1918-1969; Series I
  - A
    - 1918-1941 (Box 1, Folder 1-13)
    - 1941-1954 (Box 2, Folder 14-25)
    - 1955-1969 (Box 3, Folder 26-36)
  - American Association of University Professors, 1930-1932 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - American Historical Association, 1930-1935 (Box 3, Folder 38-39)
  - Archives, 1930-1932 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - B
    - 1917-1937 (Box 4, Folder 41-52)
    - 1937-1945 (Box 5, Folder 53-62)
    - 1946-1955 (Box 6, Folder 63-71)
    - 1956-1969 (Box 7, Folder 72-80)
  - Bemis family, 1930-1932 (Box 7, Folder 81)
  - Boggs, S.W., 1949 (Box 7, Folder 82)
  - C
    - 1918-1942 (Box 8, Folder 83-92)
    - 1942-1954 (Box 9, Folder 93-103)
    - 1955-1969 (Box 10, Folder 104-114)
  - Carnegie Endowment, 1937-1938 (Box 10, Folder 115-118)
  - D
    - 1918-1951 (Box 11, Folder 119-139)
    - 1952-1969 (Box 12, Folder 140-153)
  - E-F
    - 1918-1941 (Box 13, Folder 154-169)
    - 1941-1952 (Box 14, Folder 170-181)
    - 1953-1969 (Box 15, Folder 182-195)
  - Elliot, T.C., 1930-1932 (Box 15, Folder 196)
  - Ford, Worthington C., 1930-1932 (Box 15, Folder 197)
  - G
    - 1918-1952 (Box 16, Folder 198-219)
    - 1953-1965 (Box 17, Folder 220-32)
    - 1966-1969 (Box 18, Folder 233)
  - George Washington University, 1927-1929 (Box 18, Folder 234-235)
  - H-I-J
    - 1918-1940 (Box 19, Folder 236-249)
    - 1940-1955 (Box 20, Folder 250-265)
    - 1956 (Box 21, Folder 266-274)
  - Hoover, Herbert, 1940-1941 (Box 21, Folder 275)
  - K-L
    - 1918-1937 (Box 22, Folder 276-287)
    - 1938-1945 (Box 23, Folder 288-295)
    - 1946-1956 (Box 24, Folder 296-309)
    - 1957-1969 (Box 25, Folder 310-318)
  - Knights of Columbus Historical Commission, 1922-1923 (Box 25, Folder 319-321)
  - M
    - 1918-1941 (Box 26, Folder 322-335)
    - 1941-1953 (Box 27, Folder 336-346)
    - 1954-1969 (Box 28, Folder 347-358)
  - N-O
    - 1918-1947 (Box 29, Folder 359-376)
    - 1948-1969 (Box 30, Folder 377-394)
  - P-Q
    - 1918-1955 (Box 31, Folder 395-413)
    - 1956-1969 (Box 32, Folder 414-427)
  - R
    - 1922-1955 (Box 33, Folder 428-446)
    - 1956-1969 (Box 34, Folder 447-456)
  - S
    - 1918-1940 (Box 35, Folder 457-468)
    - 1940-1949 (Box 36, Folder 469-476)
    - 1950-1959 (Box 37, Folder 477-486)
    - 1960-1965 (Box 38, Folder 487-490)
  - Smith, George H.E., 1942-1960 (Box 38, Folder 491)
  - Spain, 1924 (Box 38, Folder 492)
  - State Department, U.S., 1940-1941 (Box 38, Folder 493)
  - Students' letters, 1930-1934 (Box 38, Folder 494)
  - T-U-V
    - 1918-1950 (Box 39, Folder 495-515)
    - 1951-1969 (Box 40, Folder 516-529)
  - W-Z
    - 1918-1943 (Box 41, Folder 530-542)
    - 1944-1959 (Box 42, Folder 543-557)
    - 1960-1969 (Box 43, Folder 558-563)
  - War papers, 1942-1943 (Box 43, Folder 564)
  - Yale University, 1940-1941 (Box 43, Folder 565-566)
- Organization and Project Files, 1918-1969; Series II
  - Adams Papers, 1942-1956 (Box 44, Folder 567-580)
  - Air War College, 1939-1956 (Box 44, Folder 581-584)
  - Alfred A. Knopf
    - 1940-1955 (Box 45, Folder 585-596)
    - 1956-1969 (Box 46, Folder 597-608)
  - American Historical Association
    - 1951-1960 November (Box 46, Folder 609-617)
    - 1960 December-1968 (Box 47, Folder 618-632)
  - Authors Guild, 1951-1966 (Box 48, Folder 633-641)
  - Autobiography, Undated (Box 49, Folder 642)
  - Benjamin Franklin Papers, 1954-1960 (Box 50, Folder 643-645)
  - Clark University, 1951-1967 (Box 50, Folder 646-649)
  - Colonial Williamsburg, 1959-1965 (Box 51, Folder 650-655)
  - Command and Staff College, 1960-1964 (Box 52, Folder 656-657)
  - Cuba and Foreign Policy, 1959-1963 (Box 52, Folder 658-664)
  - Diplomatic History of the United States: maps, charts, and other oversized material, Undated (Box 69)
  - Mounted certificate to Bemis in recognition of his study and cultivation of history from the Academia de la Historia, Havana, Cuba, 1945 February 15 (Box 69)
  - Ferrell, Robert H.
    - (A - W), 1959-1965 (Box 53, Folder 665-676)
    - 1956-1963 March (Box 54, Folder 677-685)
    - 1963 April-1965 (Box 55, Folder 686-693)
  - Henry Holt and Company
    - 1937-1944 (Box 56, Folder 697-705)
    - 1945-1954 (Box 57, Folder 706-715)
    - 1955-1968 (Box 58, Folder 716-725)
  - Indiana University Press, 1956-1968 (Box 59, Folder 726-728)
  - John Quincy Adams..., 1945-1965 (Box 59, Folder 729-736)
  - Library of Congress, 1927-1929 (Box 60, Folder 737-739)
  - "Nationalization and Conservation," typescript, correspondence, and photographs, circa 1950-1960 (Box 60, Folder 739A)
  - Photographs, 1950s (Box 60, Folder 740)
  - Truman Library, 1957-1968 (Box 61, Folder 741-752)
  - United States Army, 1954-1962 (Box 62, Folder 753-759)
  - United States Dept. of State, Mixed Claims Commission, 1909-1935 (Box 63, Folder 760-769)
  - United States Navy, Navy History Advisory Commission, 1955-1969 (Box 64, Folder 770-776)
  - United States Navy, Naval War College, 1933-1962 (Box 64, Folder 777-782)
  - United States Navy, Naval War College, 1961 (Box 65, Folder 783-784)
  - United States Navy, Naval War College. "Submarine Warfare in the Strategy of American Defense and Diplomacy", 1951 December 15 (Box 65, Folder 785)
  - United States Navy, Naval War College, 1961 (Box 65, Folder 786)
  - Woodrow Wilson Papers, 1959-1967 (Box 66, Folder 787-790)
  - Yale University, A - Z, Undated (Box 67, Folder 791-802)
  - Yale University Department of History, 1934-1963 (Box 68, Folder 803-811)